

  <othercredit role="proofreader">
    <firstname>FIX</firstname>
    <surname>ME!</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role="illustrator">
    <firstname>Rebecca</firstname>
    <surname>Demarest</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <!-- All rights reserved. -->

  <publisher>
    <publishername>O’Reilly Media, Inc.    </publishername>
    <address format="linespecific">
      <street>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</street>
      <city>Sebastopol</city>
      <state>CA</state>
      <postcode>95472</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>

  <legalnotice role="printlocation">
    <para>Printed in the United States of America.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="printer">
    <para>[?]</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="use">
    <para>O’Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales promotional use. Online editions are also available for most 
          titles (<ulink url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly" role="orm:hideurl:ital">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>). For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales department:
          800-998-9938 or <phrase role="keep-together"><email>corporate@oreilly.com</email></phrase>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="trademarks">
    <para>Nutshell Handbook, the Nutshell Handbook logo, and the O’Reilly logo
          are registered trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc. !!FILL THIS IN!!
          and related trade dress are trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc.    </para>
    <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to distinguish
          their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those designations appear
          in this book, and O’Reilly Media, Inc. was aware of a trademark claim,
          the designations have been printed in caps or initial caps.    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="damages">
    <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
        the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions, 
        or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained herein.</para>
  </legalnotice>
<isbn>9781449356811</isbn><edition>1</edition><author><firstname>Yakov</firstname><surname>Fain</surname><authorblurb><para>Yakov Fain is a Managing Director at Farata Systems, a company provides consulting and training services. He authored several books on Java and Flex and dozens of articles on software development. Sun Microsystems has nominated and awarded Mr. Fain with the title of Java Champion, which was presented to only a hundred people in the world. Yakov is Certified Adobe Flex Instructor. He holds MS in Applied Math. You can reach him at yfain@faratasystems.com.</para></authorblurb></author><author><firstname>Victor</firstname><surname>Rasputnis</surname><authorblurb><para>Dr. Victor Rasputnis is a Managing Principal of Farata Systems. He's responsible for Farata consulting and mentoring practice, providing architectural design to companies implementing RIA with Adobe Flex, Air and Livecycle technologies. He holds a PhD in Computer Science from the Moscow Institute of Robotics. Victor is Certified Adobe Flex Instructor. Victor lives in New York with his wife Aziza and his daughter Alice. He likes playing tennis and skiing with his friends. You can reach him at vrasputnis@faratasystems.com.</para></authorblurb></author><author><firstname>Anatole</firstname><surname>Tartakovsky</surname><authorblurb><para>Anatole Tartakovsky is a technology consultant, emerging technologies enthusiast and problem solver. He is a Managing Principal of Farata Systems and is responsible for creation of frameworks and reusable components. Prior Anatole played roles as Technology Consultant, Project Manager, CTO, and Mentor for various enterprises. Anatole authored number of books and articles on Flex, AJAX, XML, and client-server technologies. His education includes MS in mathematics and post graduate work in Expert Systems. You can reach him at atartakovsky@faratasystems.com.</para></authorblurb></author><author><firstname>Viktor</firstname><surname>Gamov</surname><authorblurb><para>Viktor Gamov is a senior software engineer at Farata Systems. He consults financial institutions and startups in design and implementation of Web Applications with HTML5, Flex and Java. Viktor is passionate about writing the code, open source community and JVM ecosystem. He holds MS in Computer Science. Viktor is a co-organizer of the Princeton JUG and NJ Flex meetup http://www.meetup.com/NJFlex. He tweets at @gamussa. You can reach him on email viktor.gamov@faratasystems.com.</para></authorblurb></author><editor><firstname>Mary</firstname><surname>Treseler</surname></editor><editor><firstname>Brian</firstname><surname>Anderson</surname></editor><copyright><year>2010</year><holder>Yakov Fain, Victor Rasputnis, Anatole Tartakovsky, and Viktor Gamov</holder></copyright><editor role="production"><firstname>Melanie</firstname><surname>Yarbrough</surname></editor><editor role="copy"><firstname/><surname/></editor><othercredit role="indexer"><firstname/><surname/></othercredit><othercredit role="coverdesigner"><firstname>Karen</firstname><surname>Montgomery</surname></othercredit><othercredit role="interiordesigner"><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Futato</surname></othercredit><printhistory><formalpara><title>First Edition</title><para>July, 2014</para></formalpara></printhistory><revhistory><revision><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date><revremark>First release</revremark></revision></revhistory>
