

  <othercredit role="proofreader">
    <firstname>Kim</firstname>
    <surname>Cofer</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role="illustrator">
    <firstname>Rebecca</firstname>
    <surname>Demarest</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <!-- All rights reserved. -->

  <publisher>
    <publishername>O’Reilly Media, Inc.    </publishername>
    <address format="linespecific">
      <street>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</street>
      <city>Sebastopol</city>
      <state>CA</state>
      <postcode>95472</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>

  <legalnotice role="printlocation">
    <para>Printed in the United States of America.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="printer">
    <para>[LSI]</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="use">
    <para>O’Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales promotional use. Online editions are also available for most 
          titles (<ulink url="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/?portal=oreilly" role="orm:hideurl:ital">http://my.safaribooksonline.com</ulink>). For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales department:
          800-998-9938 or <phrase role="keep-together"><email>corporate@oreilly.com</email></phrase>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="trademarks">
    <para>Nutshell Handbook, the Nutshell Handbook logo, and the O’Reilly logo
          are registered trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc. <emphasis>Enterprise Web Development</emphasis>, the cover image of a,
          and related trade dress are trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc.    </para>
    <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to distinguish
          their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those designations appear
          in this book, and O’Reilly Media, Inc. was aware of a trademark claim,
          the designations have been printed in caps or initial caps.    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="damages">
    <para>While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this book,
        the publisher and authors assume no responsibility for errors or omissions, 
        or for damages resulting from the use of the information contained herein.</para>
  </legalnotice>
<isbn>9781449356811</isbn><edition>1</edition><author><firstname>Yakov</firstname><surname>Fain</surname><authorblurb><para><emphasis role="bold">Yakov Fain</emphasis> is a cofounder of the Farata Systems and SuranceBay companies. The first company provides consulting services in the field of enterprise web development and ecommerce, and the second one is a software product company, which develops software for the insurance industry. A leader of the Princeton Java Users Group, he has authored several technical books and dozens of articles on software development. Yakov received the title of Java Champion, which has been presented to only 150 people worldwide. Yakov also holds an MS in applied math. You can reach him at <emphasis>yfain@faratasystems.com</emphasis> and follow him on <ulink url="http://twitter.com/yfain">Twitter</ulink>.</para></authorblurb></author>

<author><firstname>Victor</firstname><surname>Rasputnis</surname><authorblurb><para><emphasis role="bold">Dr. Victor Rasputnis</emphasis> is a cofounder of the Farata Systems and SuranceBay companies. He spends most of his time providing architectural design, implementation management, and mentoring to companies migrating to ecommerce technologies with Hybris. Victor has authored several books and dozens of technical articles. He holds a PhD in computer science. You can reach Victor at <emphasis>vrasputnis@faratasystems.com</emphasis>.</para></authorblurb></author>

<author><firstname>Anatole</firstname><surname>Tartakovsky</surname><authorblurb><para><emphasis role="bold">Anatole Tartakovsky</emphasis> is a cofounder of the Farata Systems and SuranceBay companies. He spent more than 25 years developing system and business software. In the last 15 years, his focus has been on creating frameworks and business applications for dozens of enterprises ranging from Walmart to Wall Street firms. Anatole has authored a number of books and articles on Ajax, Flex, XML, the Internet, and client-server technologies. He holds an MS in mathematics. You can reach Anatole at <emphasis>atartakovsky@faratasystems.com</emphasis>.</para></authorblurb></author>

<author><firstname>Viktor</firstname><surname>Gamov</surname><authorblurb><para><emphasis role="bold">Viktor Gamov</emphasis> is a senior software engineer at Farata Systems. He consults financial institutions and startups in design and implementation of web applications with HTML5 and Java. A co-organizer of the Princeton Java Users Group, Viktor is passionate about writing code and about the open source community. He holds an MS in computer science. You can reach Viktor at <emphasis>viktor.gamov@faratasystems.com</emphasis> and follow him on <ulink url="http://twitter.com/gamussa">Twitter</ulink>.</para></authorblurb></author><editor><firstname>Mary</firstname><surname>Treseler</surname></editor><editor><firstname>Brian</firstname><surname>Anderson</surname></editor><copyright><year>2014</year><holder>Yakov Fain, Victor Rasputnis, Anatole Tartakovsky, and Viktor Gamov</holder></copyright><editor role="production"><firstname>Melanie</firstname><surname>Yarbrough</surname></editor><editor role="copy"><firstname>Sharon</firstname><surname>Wilkey</surname></editor><othercredit role="indexer"><firstname>Judith</firstname><surname>McConville</surname></othercredit><othercredit role="coverdesigner"><firstname>Karen</firstname><surname>Montgomery</surname></othercredit><othercredit role="interiordesigner"><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Futato</surname></othercredit><printhistory><formalpara><title>First Edition</title><para>June, 2014</para></formalpara></printhistory><revhistory><revision><date>2014-06-25</date><revremark>First release</revremark></revision></revhistory>
